<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<helpfile>
    <title>HMSCalculate User Guide!</title>
    <version>1.1</version>
    <last_revised>April 23, 2015</last_revised>
    <author>Field15, Inc.</author>
    <copyright>Field15, Inc. 2015</copyright>
    <topic id="1">
        <index_title>Welcome to HMSCalculate</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p>]]><![CDATA[<b>]]>Welcome to the HMSCalculate User Guide!<![CDATA[</b>]]><![CDATA[<br />]]>
            Version 1.1<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            Last updated on April 23, 2015<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>Select a help topic to the left to learn more about how to use HMSCalculate.
            All of the information provided here is also available online at
            <![CDATA[<a>]]>http://dave.caretcake.com<![CDATA[</a>]]>. Registered users may also visit 
            <![CDATA[<a>]]>http://www.field15.com<![CDATA[</a>]]> for additional support.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="2">
        <index_title>Overview</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>OVERVIEW<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate is a tool for adding, subtracting, multiplying, and
            dividing units of time in hours, minutes, and seconds (HMS).<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The calculator consists of three main parts from top to bottom:
            1. The input fields to enter hour, minute, second, and integer
            data.  2.  The input buttons (numbers, clear functions,
            mathematical functions, etc.).  3. The output field that shows
            a running a total of your calculations along with all of the
            entries that have gone into the current total displayed.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>At the top of the calculator you have additional functions under the
            "File" and "Help" menus.  The "File" menu contains one additional
            option labeled "Exit" which closes the calculator program.  (You
            can do the same thing by clicking on your operating system's
            standard close window button for this program.)  The "Help" menu
            contains an option labeled "Help" which displays the contents of
            the HMSCalculate's User Guide and another option called "About"
            which provides you with general information about the version
            of the calculator that you are using.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="3">
        <index_title>Entering Data</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>ENTERING DATA<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>When HMSCalculate first starts, you're presented with three
            input fields separated by colons at the top of the screen.  The
            first field is for hours, the second is for minutes, and the third
            is for seconds.  By default, no input field is selected, so use your
            mouse to click in the field you'd like to enter data for first.
            HMSCalculate will indicate which field is selected, by showing you
            a blinking cursor in the selected field.  From there, you can enter
            data into the field either by using your mouse to click on the
            number buttons on the screen or by simply typing the numbers directly
            on your computer's keyboard.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate accepts both whole numbers and decimals 
            in the input fields.  That means that both "3" and "3.25" are
            valid entries in a single input field.  Keep in mind that decimals
            are understood as fractional amounts of the division of time in which
            the data is found.  In other words, "3.5" in the hours field is
            understand as three and one half hours which can also be expressed as
            three hours and thirty minutes.  "3.5" in the minutes field, would
            be understood as three and half minutes which can also be expressed
            as three minutes and thirty seconds.  "3.5" seconds is simply
            understood as three and one half seconds. A second is the smallest
            unit of time HMSCalculate operates in; it does not work in milliseconds
            or smaller.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>In the multiplication and division modes, the three standard input
            fields (hours, minutes, and seconds) are replaced by a single
            input field.  This is explained in detail in the multiplication
            and division sections of this guide.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="4">
        <index_title>Addition</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>ADDITION<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate is capable of adding hours, minutes, and seconds
            in two separate formats.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The first format uses whole numbers only.  For example, if you
            wanted to add 1 hour, 10 minutes, and 15 seconds to 2 hours,
            20 minutes, and 15 seconds (01:10:15 + 02:15:00), you could begin by  
            using your mouse to click in the hours input field to indicate you're
            going to start entering hour data.  Then, using either your computer's
            keyboard or the buttons on the screen, you would enter the whole
            number "1" in the hours field.  Use the tab key on your keyboard
            or your mouse to move to the minutes field and enter "10".  Finally,
            use the tab key on your keyboard or your mouse to move to the
            seconds field and enter "15".  Next press the "+" key on your keyboard
            or use your mouse to click on the plus button in the HMSCalculate
            program.  You will immediately notice that the hour, minute, and
            second input fields have been cleared out, but the output field
            at the bottom of the program has been updated to say:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] 01:10:15<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] 1.17<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] 70.25<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] 4215<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 01:10:15<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>This indicates that your first data entry has been accepted.  (For a
            complete description of the output field, please see the "Calculation 
            Totals" section in this guide.)<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>To continue with your calculation, simply follow the same instructions
            as above, but this time input 2 hours, 15 minutes, and 0 seconds and
            press the "+" button to see your new totals.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>Entering whole numbers is relatively straightforward and is probably
            the input format needed for most purposes.  However, sometimes you
            may also need the ability to add decimals.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>Decimal data indicates a fraction of some unit of time.  For example,
            "1.5" hours is understood as one-and-a-half hours or one and 50%
            of an hour, both of which equal one hour and 30 minutes.
            This means that the value from the sample above, 02:15:00, could
            also have been entered into the hours field as "2.25" with zeroes
            in both the minutes and seconds fields, because 25% of one hour is
            equal to 15 minutes.  In short, 2.25 hours equals 02:15:00.  Moreover,
            whole and decimal data can even be mixed in different fields at the
            same time.  Let's say that you wanted to enter the value two
            hours, thirty minutes, and no seconds.  You could enter that as
            "2.25" in the hours field, "15" in the minutes field and "0" in the
            seconds field.  You could even enter it as "2.25" in the hours field,
            "14.5" in the minutes field and "30" in the seconds field.  Ultimately,
            all of these ways of entering the input still equal two hours and
            thirty minutes expressed different ways.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate is designed to be flexible enough to adapt
            to a wide range of needs.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="5">
        <index_title>Subtraction</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>SUBTRACTION<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate is capable of subtracting hours, minutes, and seconds
            in two separate formats.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The first format uses whole numbers only.  For example, if you
            wanted to subtract 1 hour, 10 minutes, and 15 seconds from 2 hours,
            20 minutes, and 15 seconds (01:10:15 + 02:15:00), you could begin by  
            using your mouse to click in the hours input field to indicate you're
            going to start entering hour data.  Then, using either your computer's
            keyboard or the buttons on the screen, you would enter the whole
            number "2" in the hours field.  Use the tab key on your keyboard
            or your mouse to move to the minutes field and enter "15".  Finally,
            use the tab key on your keyboard or your mouse to move to the
            seconds field and enter "00".  Next press the "-" key on your keyboard
            or use your mouse to click on the minus button in the HMSCalculate
            program.  You will immediately notice that the hour, minute, and
            second input fields have been cleared out, but the output field
            at the bottom of the program has been updated to say:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] 02:15:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] 2.15<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] 135.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] 8100<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 02:15:00<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>This indicates that your first data entry has been accepted.  (For a
            complete description of the output field, please see the "Calculation 
            Totals" section in this guide.)<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>To continue with your calculation, simply follow the same instructions
            as above, but this time input 1 hours, 10 minutes, and 15 seconds and
            press the "-" button to see your new totals.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>Entering whole numbers is relatively straightforward and is probably
            the input format needed for most purposes.  However, sometimes you
            may also need the ability to subtract decimals.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>Decimal data indicates a fraction of some unit of time.  For example,
            "1.5" hours is understood as one-and-a-half hours or one and 50%
            of an hour, both of which equal one hour and 30 minutes.
            This means that the value from the sample above, 02:15:00, could
            also have been entered into the hours field as "2.25" with zeroes
            in both the minutes and seconds fields, because 25% of one hour is
            equal to 15 minutes.  In short, 2.25 hours equals 02:15:00.  Moreover,
            whole and decimal data can even be mixed in different fields at the
            same time.  Let's say that you wanted to enter the value two
            hours, thirty minutes, and no seconds.  You could enter that as
            "2.25" in the hours field, "15" in the minutes field and "0" in the
            seconds field.  You could even enter it as "2.25" in the hours field,
            "14.5" in the minutes field and "30" in the seconds field.  Ultimately,
            all of these ways of entering the input still equal two hours and
            thirty minutes expressed different ways.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate is designed to be flexible enough to adapt
            to a wide range of needs.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="6">
        <index_title>Multiplication</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>MULTIPLICATION<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate is capable of multiplying hours, minutes, and seconds
            by whole and decimal numbers.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>By default, hour, minute, and second data is entered into the
            program through one of three input fields at the top of HMSCalculate.
            However, when you press the "*" button on your computer's keyboard
            or click on the times button on the calculator, the three default
            input fields change into a single input field.  This alternate input
            field allows you to enter a whole or decimal value to multiply the
            the current calculation total by. For example, if the calculation
            total area in HMSCalculate read:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] 03:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] 3.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] 180.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] 10800<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 01:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 02:00:00<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>This would indicate you have already added 1 hour to 2 hours with
            a current total of 3 hours for the sum of your calculations. (For a
            complete description of the output field, please see the "Calculation 
            Totals" section in this guide.)  If you wanted to multiply this total
            (3 hours) by "10", you would simply press the "*" key on your
            computer's keyboard or use the mouse to press the multiply button
            on HMSCalculate, enter "10" into the alternate input field at the
            top of the program, and continue with your calculations.  The result
            would look like this:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] 30:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] 30.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] 1800.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] 108000<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 01:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 02:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            x 10<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>This same process can be used to multiply by decimal amounts as well,
            such as "10.5" or "10.25".<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="7">
        <index_title>Division</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>DIVISION<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>HMSCalculate is capable of dividing hours, minutes, and seconds
            by whole and decimal numbers.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>By default, hour, minute, and second data is entered into the
            program through one of three input fields at the top of HMSCalculate.
            However, when you press the "/" button on your computer's keyboard
            or click on the division button on the calculator, the three default
            input fields change into a single input field.  This alternate input
            field allows you to enter a whole or decimal value to divide the
            the current calculation total by. For example, if the calculation
            total area in HMSCalculate read:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] 03:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] 3.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] 180.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] 10800<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 01:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 02:00:00<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>This would indicate you have already added 1 hour to 2 hours with
            a current total of 3 hours for the sum of your calculations. (For a
            complete description of the output field, please see the "Calculation 
            Totals" section in this guide.)  If you wanted to divide this total
            (3 hours) by "3", you would simply press the "/" key on your
            computer's keyboard or use the mouse to press the division button
            on HMSCalculate, enter "3" into the alternate input field at the
            top of the program, and continue with your calculations.  The result
            would look like this:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] 1:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] 1.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] 60.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] 3600<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 01:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 02:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            / 3<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>This same process can be used to divide by decimal amounts as well,
            such as "3.5" or "3.25".<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="8">
        <index_title>Calculation Totals</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>CALCULATION TOTALS<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The calculation totals field at the bottom of HMSCalculate is the
            heart of the program.  This is where you're able to track your
            calculation's totals along with everything you've entered into the
            current calculation.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The total is displayed in a scrollable area in the format:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] <![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] <![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] <![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] <![CDATA[<br />]]>
            . . . input log . . .<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The value represented by the "[HMS]" is the current total for your
            calculations in the Hour:Minute:Second format.  The "[HOURS]",
            "[MINUTES]", and "[SECONDS]" lines show the current total for your
            calculations in one division of time only (hours, minutes, and
            seconds respectively).  These four elements are always displayed
            at the top of the calculations total field.  Below them is a log
            of all the amounts that have gone into the current calculation.
            The logs indicate the type of calculation and the value that took
            place.  For example:<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>[HMS] 5:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [HOURS] 5.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [MINUTES] 300.00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            [SECONDS] 18000<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            + 05:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            - 01:00:00<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            x 10<![CDATA[<br />]]>
            / 8<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>This log would indicate that you first entered 5 hours, then
            subtracted 1 hour.  From there, you multiplied the total by 10 and
            then divided the result by 8.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The log is useful for at least two reasons.  The first is to give
            you an easy way to visually double-check long calculations for
            typos and mistaken entries.  The secon reason is to give you the
            ability to edit prior entries without having to re-enter the
            entire calculation from the beginning.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>To edit an entry in the log, simply click on the entry you would
            like to edit.  This will cause HMSCalculate to populate the input
            fields with whatever was entered at that point in time.  (NOTE:
            HMSCalculate will automatically convert from the default hour,
            minute, and second input fields to the individual input field
            required for multiplaction and division if you are editing an
            entry of either of those types.)  From there, change the original
            value to the new one and press either the "=" button to end your calculation
            as-is or press one of the addition, subtraction, multiplication,
            or division buttons in the program or on your computer's keyboard
            to edit the log entry and continue with your calculation.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="9">
        <index_title>Other Functions</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>OTHER FUNCTIONS<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>In addition to the input fields, number and calculation type input
            buttons, and calculation totals field, HMSCalculate also provides
            you with buttons labeled "C", "AC", and "=".<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The "C" and "AC" stand for Clear and All Clear.  Pressing the "C"
            button will cause the input fields only to be cleared.  Your overall
            calculation and calculation totals will remain in-tact.  Pressing
            the "AC" button will clear the input fields along with the calculation
            totals field.  In other words, you will completely clear everything
            related to the current calculation so that you can start a new
            one from scratch.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
            
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>The "=" button simply tells HMSCalculate that you are done with the
            current calculation.  If there's a value in the input field, it will
            incorporate that value into the current calculation and show you the
            final total of your calculation.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
    <topic id="10">
        <index_title>Additional Support</index_title>
        <content>
            <![CDATA[<p><b>]]>ADDITIONAL SUPPORT<![CDATA[</p></b>]]>
        
            <![CDATA[<p>]]>Some additional support is available online at <![CDATA[<a>]]>http://dave.caretcake.com<![CDATA[</a>]]>.  
            Registered users may also visit <![CDATA[<a>]]>http://www.field15.com<![CDATA[</a>]]> for official support.<![CDATA[</p>]]>
        </content>
    </topic>
</helpfile>
